Guide to the Prize-Winning Student Essays Collection MC 86
New York University Archives
Prize-Winning Student Essays Collection
1900-1963
1922-1960
New York University Archives
New York University. Washington Square College of Arts and Science
New York University. University College of Arts and Pure Science
MC 86
1.75 Linear Feet in three manuscript boxes and two half manuscript boxes
The Prize Winning Student Essays Collection contains student writing dating between 1900 and 1963, which received one of six annual prizes given by New York University: the James Gordon Bennett Prize, the Minnie Kramer Cowin Prize, the Frederick Seward Gibson Prize, the Helen M. Jones Prize in History, the Maas Essay Prize in American History, and the New York University Philosophical Society Prize. Each prize was awarded for student work in specific fields of the humanities and social sciences including political science, history, English literature, and philosophy.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The provenance of the Prize Winning Student Essays Collection is unknown. However, it has existed in its current format in the University Archives since at least 1987.
Arrangement
Materials are arranged chronologically within each series. Series include:
Series I: James Gordon Bennett Prize Essays
Series II: Minnie Kramer Cowin Prize Essays
Series III: Frederick Seward Gibson Prize Essays
Series IV: Helen M. Jones Prize in History
Series V: Maas Essay Prize
Series VI: New York University Philosophical Society Essay Prize
Historical Note
The undergraduate colleges of New York University have offered various prizes for student writing over time. The history of the six essay prizes included in this collection is listed below.
The James Gordon Bennett Prize was endowed in 1893 by James Gordon Bennett, publisher of the New York Herald, and awarded for the first time at Commencement in 1894. It recognizes the best essay by an undergraduate senior, "in English prose upon some subject of American governmental, domestic, or foreign policy of contemporaneous interest." The topic for submitted essays was assigned by the faculty each year. Winning students received $50. While the most recent Bennett Prize essay in the University Archives' collection dates from 1956, the prize is still awarded today.
The Minnie Kramer Cowin Prize was awarded at Commencement for an essay in political science. Two members of the Class of 1923, Harold L. and William T. Cowin, endowed the prize in memory of their mother. When it was first offered in 1924, student essays were solicited on a topic determined by the faculty in advance. However, beginning in 1928, the prize was simply awarded to the best essay submitted in fulfillment of a class assignment. It included a $50 honorarium. The last Minnie Kramer Cowin Prize was awarded in 1974.
The Frederick Seward Gibson Prize was endowed by the estate of Frederick Seward Gibson, an alumnus of the University College Class of 1896. It was first awarded in 1901, to a student who produced high quality writing in the field of English literature. Like other prizes which were offered throughout several decades of the university's history, the terms of the competition have undergone slight changes over time. The Gibson Prize was originally awarded to "an essay of high literary merit on a subject proposed by the professor of English literature as a proper subject for treatment in a literary form and approved by the college faculty." Beginning in 1931, original works of creative writing were accepted as well. Competition was originally open to seniors only, but eligibility was expanded to include any student above the freshman year in 1924; sophomores were again excluded in 1933. The prize included $70, reduced to $60 in 1933. It is still awarded for the best piece of critical or creative writing by a junior or senior student.
The Helen M. Jones Prize in History was awarded from 1952-1959 to the best essay on a selected topic in French history. As of 1960, it is instead awarded to the student who, in the opinion of the Department of History, had made the best record in the history honors course. It included a monetary prize based on the income of a $1000 gift given by Theodore F. Jones, a member of the University College Department of History, in memory of his mother. It is still awarded today.
The Maas Essay Prize was first opened to competition in the academic year 1955-1956. It was endowed by the will of Kittyn Maas, widow of Charles Oscar Maas, in memory of her husband. It included a prize of $350 to be awarded to an undergraduate student "who submits the best essay on a specific topic relating to the heritage and tradition of the United States of America." The last prize was awarded in 1974.
Scope and Contents
The Prize Winning Student Essays Collection contains student writing dating between 1900 and 1963, which received one of six annual prizes given by New York University: the James Gordon Bennett Prize, the Minnie Kramer Cowin Prize, the Frederick Seward Gibson Prize, the Helen M. Jones Prize in History, the Maas Essay Prize in American History, and the New York University Philosophical Society Prize. Each prize was awarded for student work in specific fields of the humanities and social sciences. The majority of the collection consists of typed, handwritten and bound essays, with the exception of some poetry and fiction pieces which were awarded the Frederick Seward Gibson Prize. The Prize Winning Student Essays Collection is not an exhaustive collection of the various prizes awarded for student work throughout the history of the university, nor does it include a copy of every essay to which the prizes in the collection were awarded. The collection's provenance is not known, though it has existed in its current format in the University Archives since at least 1987.
Poems.; Political science students; Poetry -- Study and teaching; 20th century.; Philosophy -- Study and teaching.; Essays.; History -- Study and teaching; English literature -- Study and teaching; New York University -- Students
- James Gordon Bennett Prize Essays, 1900-1956; 0.5 Linear Feet in one manuscript box
  Scope and Contents
  The James Gordon Bennett Prize was awarded to student work on contemporary American government, domestic policy, and foreign policy. Materials include award winning essays dating from 1900-1956, with the bulk of the material dating from 1925-1942.
  - "The Government of Federal Dependencies," Henry Noble MacCracken (not a prize essay), 1900 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "The Government of Federal Dependencies," Joseph H. Altman, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "The Government of Federal Dependencies," Stanley H. Molleson, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "The Relation of the Tariff to the Trusts," William H. Orr, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "The Interpretation of the Hay-Paunceforth Treaty in Regard to the Panama Canal Tolls," Joseph R. Amilcaro, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "History of Federal Attempts to Regulate Child Labor," Clifford Rowe, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "The World Court as an American Ideal," Joseph Lotterman, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Recent Centralising Tendencies in State Administration," Nathaniel Jones, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "American Merchant Marine Policy since the World War," Sidney Louis Feiler, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "American Policy regarding the Debts of Nations Allied with the United States during the World War," Sidney Greenman, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "History of the Attempts at Reorganisation of the Federal Administrative Services since 1905," Myron Krotinger, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "American Recognition of the U. S. S. R.," Edwin A. Gross, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "The Attitude of the American Government towards Manchukus," Alvin J. Bernstein, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - "Federal Regulation of Companies Engaged in the Production and Distribution of Electric Power," Norman Moloshok, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "Federal Regulation of Radio Broadcasting with Special References to the Question of Freedom of Speech," Robert J. Kaller, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - "American Legislation on the Subject of Old Age Pension," Justin M. Golenbosk, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "American Foreign Policy Concerning Outposts of Defense in the Atlantic Ocean and the Caribbean Sea since 1898," Robert M. Bor, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - "The Problem of Self Government for the District of Columbia," Robert Price, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - "The Problem of Statehood for Hawaii," David L. Mitchell, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - "Merits and Defects of the Proposal to Fix a National Minimum Age of Eighteen for the Suffrage," Stephen Roger Langenthal, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Minnie Kramer Cowin Prize Essays, 1925-1960; 0.5 Linear Feet in one manuscript box
  The Minnie Kramer Cowin Prize was awarded to the best student essay in political science. Materials include award winning essays dating from 1925-1960, with the bulk of the material dating from 1925-1941.
  - "The Budget Law of 1921 as a check on Congressional Extravagance," Clifford Rowe, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - "The Administration of American Immigration Laws," Joseph Wortis, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - "Present Legal Status of Trade Unions in the American States," Howard Jerome Lichenstein, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - "Present Legal Status of Trade Unions in the American States," Bernard I. Strauss, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - "The Political Thought of Walter Lippmann," Leonard Zissu, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - "The Election of 1916," Eugene M. Parter, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - "Colussus vs. Midget," Jerome H. Adler, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - "The International Institute of Agriculture," Phillip Arnon, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - "Some Suggestions for the Application of Article 19 of the May 3rd, 1937 Covenant of the League of Nations,' Daniel Irving Glass (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - "France and the League of Nations since the Italo-Ethiopian Affair," Daniel Irving Glass, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - "Administrative Tribunals - Their Problems," Justin M. Golenblock, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - "Oligarchical Tendencies in Democracies," Robert H. Herskovits, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - "The Lusk Committee and Civil Rights," Robert Antin, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - "The Origin of Separation of Powers in the American Government," Wilbur G. Avery, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - "Senate Confirmation Debate on David E. Lilienthal," Lawrence H. Fuchs, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - "Private Bills in the First Session of the 81st Congress," Leo Silverstein, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - "Due Process and the Relation of the Bill of Rights to the States," Sholom Beinfeld, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Untitled Essay by Irwin Brod, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - "Israel: Parties, Politics and Policies," David Hittner, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Frederick Seward Gibson Prize Essays, 1901-1963; 0.5 Linear Feet in one manuscript box
  The Frederick Seward Gibson Prize poetry and fiction pieces broadly encompass the field of English literature, including critical essays as well as some original poetry and short stories. Materials include award winning essays dating from 1901-1963, with the bulk of the material dating from 1924-1942.
  - "Henry James as Novelist," B. R. Weel (pseudonym), undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - "The Province of the Literary Element in Historical Writings," author unknown, 1901 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - "The Province of the Literary Element in Historical Writings," Adams, 1st prize, 1901 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - "The Province of the Literary Element in Historical Writings," author unknown, 2nd prize, 1901 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - "The Province of the Literary Element in Historical Writings," B. F., 3rd prize, 1901 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - "The Poetry of Mr. Masefield," A. P. Levien, 1915 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - "Don Juan and Social Hypocrisy," Julius Haberman, 1922 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - "Frank Norris: The Significance of His Work," Arthur H. Hirchfield, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - "The Style of Joseph Conrad," Joseph Lotterman, 1925 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - "Willa Cather," Clifford Rowe, 1926 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - "Robert Frost," Elliot C. Graham, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - "Eugene O'Neill," Joseph Feldman, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - "A Critical Survey of the Plays of A. A. Milne," Philip F. Papini, 1929 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - "Galsworthy the Novelist as Social Reformer," Milton Leonard Rein, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - "Clara: A Narrative Poem," Benjamin Radin, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - "The Feather Pate of Folly," Harlan Umansky, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - "Black Out," Amos Cahan, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - "Tamar -- A Fragment," Irving A. Fosberg, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - "Poem for Passover," Leslie Fiedler, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - "The Barrel," Arthur M. Bernstein, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - "A Potpourri of Pieria," Ellis Ostrove, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - "With or Without Banners," John C. O'Brien, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - "Of Whimpers and Trumpet Calls," Alvin H. Schucman, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - "The Demons," Robert Sheckley, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - "The Fuschia Spangles," Ross Scott, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - "Shades of Goodman Brown," David Leeb, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - "Jeanne D'Arc au Bucher," Charles Mauskoph, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - "He Just Didn't Know," Phillippe Citron, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - "The Bridge," Richard S. Abrams, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - "Divine Lady," Jerome Cass, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - "Fool's Mate," Paul Winston, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - "A Mountain for Beatrice," Roger Rosenblatt, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - "The Last Trial of William the Terrible," Alan Wienblatt, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - "Romantic Triptych," Paul Watsky, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 34)
- Helen M. Jones Prize in History, 1952-1958; 0.20 Linear Feet in one half manuscript box
  The Helen M. Jones essays are on topics in French and American history, respectively. Materials include award winning essays dating from 1952-1958, with the bulk of the material dating from 1952-1953.
  - "Divergent Estimates of Napoleon III," Burton S. Sklarin, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - "French Foreign Relations in the Years Between 1713-1740," Lola Montez, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence regarding changes in qualifications for the Helen M. Jones Prize, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Maas Essay Prize, 1960; 0.05 Linear Feet in one manuscript box
  Maas Prize essays are on topics in French and American history, respectively. Materials include award winning essays dating from 1960.
  - "Coxey's Army: Symbol of Hard Times," Valarie Andrews Fleishman, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- New York University Philosophical Society Prize Essay, 1913-1933; 0.25 Linear Feet in one half manuscript box
  The New York University Philosophical Society Prize was awarded for critical and personal works in philosophy. Materials include bound award winning essays dating from 1922-1933, with the bulk of the materials dating from 1921-1933.
  - "The Philosophy of Prayer," Calphurnia L. Fairchild, 1911 (Box 5)
  - "A Criticism of Fichte's 'Science of Knowledge,' with Especial Attention to its Value as the Basis for a Philosophy of Life," R. S. Ellis, 1913 (Box 5)
  - "Is a History of the Philosophy of History Worthwhile?," Howard T. Kuist, 1921 (Box 5)
  - "A Particularistic Criticism of Confucius," Lester Eugene Denon, 1922 (Box 5)
  - "Philosophy in Contemporary Poetry," Emma L. Antz, 1923 (Box 5)
  - "An Ethical Philosophy of Life," S. L. Halkin, 1926 (Box 5)
  - "My Personal Philosophy of Life," Lillian Edmands, 1927 (Box 5)
  - "Science and the Scientific Hypothesis," A.A. Imberman, 1931 (Box 5)
  - "An Essay on the Theory of Correspondence in McTaggart's Nature of Existence," Rubin Goetsky, 1927-1928 (Box 5)
  - "Croce's Aesthetic," Joseph Mindell, 1929-1930 (Box 5)
  - "Implication," Arthur Lapan, 1931-1932 (Box 5)
  - "The Natural and Conceptual Element in the Philosophy of Aristotle," Adrienne Koch, 1932-1933 (Box 5)